vendoring go mod vendor specifically why
would you do it it doesn't seem to make
sense and somebody might suggest it to
you you're like why on Earth would I do
this um I just completed another video
uh about dealing with building private
repos for go projects and you can go
watch that video ahead of this time
ahead of this video but let me talk to
you about some of the problems that you
might have so here as as I did before we
have we have a a sort of mock
uh program that has a dependency on a
private go package again another video
completely about that you can go watch
that and you can go see that but this
actually will work after we dealt with
all the errors and set go private and
and did all the things necessary to get
this to build so in fact I have a build
command still here um go build- o hello
and this will pull it down and get it
and and you can see that in the go. some
file uh we were able to get this private
repo this this is a private package but
we're still able to get it because we
said go private and because this account
is a member of the organization that
shares ownership uh a read only access
to this other package which I
demonstrated here so here are the
different access this and stuff like
this I don't want to redo the other
video too much that I went through in
the det that and pretty substantial
details so go back and watch that video
so so the next question is what happens
if that package goes
away right so there there's actually two
reasons to do go vendoring and I'm going
to get into what go vendoring fixes
before we get into it okay because I
have not been a fan of vendoring my
whole life I've been like what what is
vendoring let's talk about what
vendoring is in the first place and I'm
just going to run it and you're going to
see what it does and then we're going to
talk about how that matches the
definition of vendoring so very simply
rather than having a g sum file here
actually I think let's try that let's
just remove the go. Su file and see what
happens we remove the G Su file let's
let's actually modify our go file so now
we don't have anything now if can I
build I probably can't right if I do a
gold build it's not going to work
anymore because it needs the module
right well let's actually vendor the
dependencies um so let's do go mod
vendor uh we're going to do go mod
vendor and it's like oh okay this
Imports this no module require provides
it try it by adding go get so the first
thing you can you can't vendor a thing
until you've tried to get it the first
time when you do a goget this is
important that you understand this when
you do a goget it updates the module
cache which is this mysterious thing
that lives in a place you can never
remember on your system and that
contains not only the source code for
the module that you have gotten but also
all of the you know it's compiled form
and everything so it makes it much
easier to use when you're doing your
building because go as you know uses
static linking which just stuffs
everything all in a big binary so you
still have to do the go getet and if you
have the errors that I encountered uh
any I made a whole video about the
possible errors you can get from goget
there are many of them and they are very
weird you don't even know what's causing
them a lot of times so please make sure
you watch that video uh but once you get
past those those problems you can go
ahead and you get this successful usage
of uh of the of the thing now if you're
not using Vim you might be using a tool
that automatically attempts to download
these things um even when you're editing
and that's all well and good but chances
are going to have to do go getet at some
point and then and Gog get- you which
automatically updates the latest version
which is not done unless you explicitly
do it for obvious security reasons right
but there's actually something better
than Gog get- you and what that is is
vendoring so now that now that our our I
can actually do a build here I can prove
it uh you can see there's my go build it
built really fast because the module
cache has already been downloaded and
updated but what happens if the the
project on which this project depends
goes
away what would happen you know that
does make you wonder right well one of
the solutions to get around that is
something called vendoring so let's do
that now so go mod vendor very simple
command that was added some time ago
that I I totally missed and didn't
really care about because I never really
understood it I remember reading about
special directories and how the vendor
directory had special meaning but I
never really connect
how valuable the thing was until I
started trying to build from private
repos and this is one of the major
advantages of go VOD Vendor by using go
mod vendor as a user loged I'm going to
say this like I'm going to zoom in here
so by using go mod vendor as a user who
has access to all the repos in the
organization I can add all I can pull
down all of the dependencies both on the
private repos as well as all of the
external stuff that I might have repes
on you know like stuff in the standard
library and thing and so when you do go
mod vendor what it does is it creates a
vendor directory that has everything you
have dependency on it also adds
something to note is it does not
download the test code it only downloads
the actual code and it downloads the
readme uh from the vend from the
dependency dependent modules okay now
let's let's talk about the implications
of this okay so there the first of all
let's look at the vendor directory here
so the vendor modules directory uh it
tells which one it is what package it's
on everything it's basically the same
information that is in the god. suum
file and by the way you still have to
have a go. suum file even if you have
vendored the stuff uh in fact I think
let's try this I don't think I can build
it without that with vender I'm trying
to see if go will still do the build
without the GM file this will be
interesting oh my Lord it did it oh that
is so that is absolute gold information
to know right there so so look at that I
have a require line in
here can I get rid of the require line I
wonder if I can get rid of the require
line oh my goodness gracious go build
nope can't do it uh oh wow this is a new
era I haven't had it before this is
interesting inconsistent
vendoring um this is interesting it's
marked as explicit in Vendor models but
not explicit required in go mod aha okay
so the answer is uh Thou shalt add it to
go mod interesting ignore the vendor
directory use mod equals read only or
mod equals mod to sync the vendor
directory go go mod vendor go mod vendor
what did it do did it remove
it oh I have to do another goget is this
going to update my check
sum oh this is this is interesting this
is this is another example of how this
stuff was tacked
on uh to go after it was already doing
stuff right um whoopsie all right so I'm
guessing it's going to add a somefile
yeah but I don't want to go
somefile the somefile this that's very
interesting go mod tidy I wonder if it's
going to make a su file again even
though it's been vendored it does oh how
stupid is that um that's very very
interesting okay anyway so I I mean I
don't like the the the that we have a
gome file there I I guess I don't know
anyway so that we apparently the go mod
we don't have to have the the Su file
there um I personally I would like this
G sum file to not be populated with
stuff that's in the vendor directory but
maybe I'm missing something there anyway
I mean that still builds just fine so I
got it look at how fast that it built it
right now did it build it from the stuff
in Vendor or did it build it from the
stuff in the module cache that's a real
question isn't it
right um so uh that's basically that's
because you theoretically can have
multiple versions on a package vendor
yes you could that's right that's a good
point so I guess you do need to check
some good Point thank you for that thank
you for that um yeah no but I could see
I could see that technically you could
vendor multiple versions of and uh of
something you can have like I could see
that with yaml or something so so so you
you probably should just do as as you
know they intend you can't even vendor a
thing until you can go get it for the
first time and that has been pretty easy
for us at this time because we are uh a
user that's logged into the uh
organization and and we're not doing
cicd where we' have to create a pseudo
generic user or a pad or Pat personal
access token or something like that um
and so let's go ahead and
do let's go ahead and do this so so you
see what it's done in the vendor
directory um and we can do our go
building it works so that is pretty much
it now let's let's talk about let's talk
about let's not let's talk let's stay on
topic everybody because we're doing a
video so let's let's talk about the
considerations of when you would use
vendoring and some of the reasons that I
didn't like vendoring before the reason
that I have never liked vendoring is
because I always felt like vendoring
meant that I had to copy and paste you
know the code out of some you know
dependent module and put it into a place
that I decided uh that would be used and
that is no longer true go mod vendor
which is just one command that you can
rent anywhere will automatically pull
everything down and you can see all the
stuff about uh go help uh mod vendor I I
think it is uh and it'll tell you all
vendor resets the modules main vendor
directory uh causes the vendor to print
the names of the vendor modules e caus
the flag to attempt to proceed despite
errors o caus the vendor to create a
vendor directory at the given the stad
if you can say if you don't other than
vendor uh vendor is a special name
though so I would never change that um
again the idea of vendoring is pretty
simple vendoring means taking something
from a dependency that would normally be
external to the project and bringing it
into the project that is what vendoring
means these days and why would you do
vendoring so the first reason you would
do vendoring is you wanted to simplify
your repo you wanted to take you only
really want I mean the the downside of
go mod vendor is it pulls in the whole
thing um and quite frankly that was new
information to me because before when
you did vendoring another form of
vendoring is to cut and paste out one
fun function from some other module and
just put that in your
project right and you probably should
make attribution and Licensing and all
that same stuff that you need to do but
that occasionally you only need one
function from another project and it's
actually better for you to copy that
function down especially if it's a
pretty simple one and put it in your own
code and it's not illegal to do that
it's it keeps your project simpler you
want to reduce the number of
dependencies and if you've been doing
any amount of serious go development you
know exactly what I'm talking about when
you get into the business of doing
tons and tons of go you know
dependencies you you're waiting around
forever um and so yeah you have to be
able to get a module to vendor it
because it was forced to move some stuff
to to internal instead of vendor oh
really you put some stuff yeah internal
is another special package name uh
module uh subdirector package name which
we'll talk about uh later
um but yeah so you have to be able to
access the thing that you're going to
put in
um interesting that that it doesn't
allow you to to move the internal stuff
interesting yeah anyway so so yeah your
package even if your package repo your
module is private and that can include
get a Enterprise Cloud on inner source
which makes everything private um you
know you you can still get at it right
um and as in this case my arix Rob get
J's test account has read only access to
those to any of those repos in the under
the organization and therefore I can
read it therefore I can do go get to do
the update and then I Can Vendor it so
so the other position of the other point
of vendoring it is let's take a
hypothetical situation so let's say
let's say that you want you have a
project and you know I mean this is an
extremely hypothetical but it's a very
important one you have a very important
project that's got a dependency on uh uh
a private repo or another repo uh
actually vendoring works with public and
private obviously uh we'll get we'll get
to vendoring for private repos as as a
reason all by itself in a second so
let's just talk about the other major
reason for doing vendoring what happens
if the dependency goes
away right and you might think well I've
already got it in my stuff and
everything if you don't vendor it you
don't have a copy of the
code and unless doing some crazy
proxying of the git repos or something
like that let's let's take a very real
scenario okay let's say that you have a
dependency on and believe me mean this
has happened this has happened let's say
you have a dependency
on a an external library that has that
is discovered to have a really glaring
horrible security bug right and let's
say it's so embarrassing for the
organization that you are dependent on
that they drop it they get rid of it
they go private it goes dark and you
don't have access to the thing anymore
and your project now no longer has
access to the source code that was used
to build
it think about I I really want to pause
for that to sink in for a second if you
are on a huge project and you have a
dependency on a public repo or private
repo that is completely organized and
maintained by somebody else and for
whatever reason they stop publishing
that
package you're screwed I mean you're
really screwed because even though you
may have built with the last cash
version when you go to try to build
again you're out of
luck and that that that module cach that
we talked about that only lives on your
specific machine for the time that you
were building it and if that were to
happen I can almost guarantee you
there's going to be a lot of a lot of
really panicked developers going diving
into their cash looking for the source
file so they can create their own
vendored solution or replacements for
the for the package that's now
unsupported and
unavailable that is a very real risk to
a to a project and it is one of the main
reasons that you should be very very
very very careful about adding
dependencies to any other project
ever um uh experience with C dependency
management to implement it by yourself
yeah because that kind of thing you
think it's unlikely to happen but it's a
very real thing another another likely
scenario let's say somebody has um uh
let's say somebody has a very you know
horrible security flaw right and they're
so embarrassed by the security plaw that
they take their whole thing down and you
now have the security vulnerability and
maybe for security reasons or maybe just
shame reasons they don't want to say how
bad it was and then your project pulls
up in a security audit that's having a
vulnerability for whatever reason right
and then you're trying to trace where
the vulnerability came from and you're
you're looking through your own
dependency tree right you're looking
through your own dependency tree you're
looking through your own PR history and
your commits and everything and you can
see that that perhaps the audit ran
against a version before this and and
the only the only evidence that you have
of the problem at all is in the checkm
folder right so if I do I'm going to go
get again so I can go update it um let
me see sorry get uh go get so let's
let's do this again so just so I can
update this now this has only got one
but if you've seen bigger projects the
only evidence that you would have of a
change that in that brought about the
security vulnerability in your project
is going to be a line item a singular
line item in your go require or in your
go some file that's going to show that
something changed so when you're doing
root cause Anis and you're trying to
find out what changed and you're looking
in your project the only thing that you
can look for is what is in the goome
file and what is in the go required file
and at best at best since they pulled
the project at best the only thing that
you can actually further research as to
why this problem even happened is you
can just say well it looks like it might
have been one of these possible
dependencies that is now gone now I in a
perfect world that project would still
be available and you could go deep dive
into their PR get history and source
code history tree like that but if but
in an imperfect World they've already
pulled it and you don't have access to
it anymore enter go vendoring if you
have been using go vendoring then For
Better or Worse all of that code is now
saved with your project for better
because you can now see instead of
having to see the line item change and
go sum which could maybe trigger you but
then as soon as you see that there's a
change in your G suum file you could
then you could then Deep dive into your
vendor directory and see the exact
changes in fact when you update your go
mod vendor you should commit a PR you
should commit one PR for your go mod
vendor updates because that PR will
contain a very
exhaustive dip of every single
dependency that has changed and all and
that can be rather large and that's the
downside of this the downside of this is
that when you add all these this you can
add some dependencies it could be
several thousand lines of code and now
that code is all permanently stored in
your repo bloating your repo Beyond you
know the where it might need to be and I
don't even know when go does caching
this is something I'd probably have to
research but I don't know how many um uh
yeah I I don't know how many of these um
like when you're I I don't know what
happens with G module caching of a thing
that has vendored stuff in it I don't
know I don't know so like for example if
you were to do a go this is something I
need to research but if you do like it's
like so somebody does a go get against
my stuff right here right is if if they
if they have a dependency on my thing
are they also going to pull in my vendor
tree and I think the answer is yes I
think that the vendor tree would travel
with it so you can see that this this
also has a downside because you're now
this is the reason I don't like I
haven't liked you know cart blanch
vendoring of everything the way go mod
vendor has worked and it might be that
this is is the thing that ultimately
makes me decide to use a more precise
version of vendoring or go back to using
you know generic accounts for dynamic
cicd builds without having vendoring at
all which is we're going to get to there
that's another major reason to use
vendoring um but but this meth this this
part of vendoring uh comes with bloat it
does it comes with bloat it's a minimal
amount of bloat but it and it's but it's
it's bloat right on the one hand it's
it's good bloat because it gives you
exactly the code that was in your
project at a given point in time exactly
the exact code is saved with your
project so you can go look at it at any
moment you can do audits against your
own code base face it would be really
interested to see if hey how's it going
tiny fall it would be really interesting
to see if um Auditors security Auditors
who are who are passing you know who are
sending who are who are examining Go
stuff uh bypass the vendor directory
because I imagine a lot of security
audits would probably look into the
vendor directory if they're if they're
security auditing a go module because
they would want to ensure that the
vendor
dependencies uh which are also in the
check some files so I imagine you know
go auditing would probably just be good
to look at the checks some file and see
if you're at the right version um
assuming that the check on file is in
sync with anything that's in your vendor
directory which according to everything
I've I've seen so far it is um so again
like you get you get all the code for
better or worse it's in there right um
so so that is the primary idea behind
vendoring the primary idea behind
vendoring is to save the code on which I
have a dependent
with the project for better or worse for
all the reasons that I talked about so
you always have a copy of the code no
matter what happens if your dependencies
go away if you're the people that own
your packages your package dependencies
die if their if their GitHub repos blow
up you still have the
code and if if the code was released
under open source and that were to
happen you would you would then
therefore have the option to take that
vendor directory and and do whatever you
wanted to with it because open source
and that that is you know all by itself
is is a reason to use go vendoring but
there is another reason to use go
vendoring related to GitHub Enterprise
Cloud migrations that have dependencies
and this is huge this is so huge this is
going to be our new Direction uh within
the company for our Enterprise
migrations to GitHub Enterprise cloud
and and and I'm going to take a moment
to to really talk talk about this okay
so um when you the the the most
important take and I've done a lot of
videos on this recently because this is
a very important thing so in my rather
large multinational corporation we are
moving from GitHub Enterprise server
which is effectively public when with
regard to go because everything's public
right it's all on a service just behind
a VPN but as far as go is concerned
everything's public and go the go module
system with was designed without
question to use public modules
everything else has been added on over
time to make it work and you're going to
see evidence of that all over go watch
the videos I I already said this but
there's a video I did about the five
things to consider to get around
dependencies on private modules and go
because it's not you're like swimming
Upstream there's like so many comments
on everywhere on the internet about
swimming Upstream when you're doing when
you're trying to use private modules you
can do it but it's always Against the
Grain it's always feeling like it's a
hack it's always tacked on it's always
some extra thing enter go modules go
vendors sorry go mod vendor go mod
vendor so so let's let's let's do the
math here okay so what does go mod
vendor fundamentally do it gets rid of
the necessity of having access to those
external
repos so so let's let's paint the
picture here right you've got you've got
your to you got your internal tool and
you have another Library you want to
break out some of your code into a
centralized
Library
um uh so so so then you have a
dependency on you have a dependency on
this internal library right well when
you're want to go Enterprise server all
of that stuff is public it's all public
and you can break it out you don't have
a problem right if you have a single
project like I do K login I have a
single project K login it has no
dependencies on anything that's a
standard go
thing and it's fine right it's totally
fine the the go releaser just works
because there's no dependencies on any
private modules whatsoever right it just
works and the go releaser works and it's
able to use the GitHub uncore token
which lives for the duration of the
GitHub action when it's running and it
only has access to that repo it's really
great for making release artifacts and
all kinds of stuff like that it's super
easy to use it's already automatically
there you don't have to create a
personal access token and add it it's
there already so if you are building a
go project that has no external
dependencies on private
repos then you can get away with just
using that you don't have to do the SSH
setup and all the other stuff that I've
done in other videos you don't have to
do any of it you just just builds it
just works with go
releaser now if you as soon as you have
a dependency on even one private repo
you now have to make all of that stuff
work right but go
vendoring makes it so that you don't
have any ex external dependencies on
anything so I let that snc in for a
second so so if you if you have um and
the reason it works is because the
bringing in the code into the vendor
thing as a part of the pr process that
bringing in of the code
that is done by a user who already has
access to all of those other external
private
things and it's actually pretty easy to
build you know locally and just by
setting go private like I did in another
video and and you can play with with go
go you know no proxy and go go no some
as well and those are all things you can
go read about elsewhere the point is
that because the vendoring action is a
develop it's in the developer space and
not the cicd process because it's
something that a a a a developer does
like you have to do go vendor it's
equivalent to copying all of those Tech
those source files into your project and
then submitting a PR for that to be an
actual part of your project you didn't
write the code but you brought it in as
if you were writing the code because all
of that happens by the
developer that happens way before cicd
ever gets a piece of it and so when cicd
is invoked as far as the GitHub action
is concerned every external dependency
is now available within a single repo
under the vendor directory and that
means that a GitHub token Works a GitHub
token works and you the same exact
action that you reuse all the time for
all your go projects now works for every
single project every single go project
you have in which you use go
vendor so so by doing that you radically
radically
simplify the steps necessary to make
this happen and if you have got if you
don't know what I'm talking about it's
very basically instead of creating
convoluted SSH and Pat and and proxies
and all these other things that are
documented in the 45 to 60 Minute video
elsewhere instead of doing any of that
and instead of wrangling with your
GitHub team to add a a different account
or to add
a justifying the addition of a readon
pat on on an organization or or you know
fighting with them or getting deployment
Keys God help you if you do that instead
of any of that go mod Vendor by doing go
mod vendor you bypass all of that you
don't have to talk to any of the teams
responsible for setting up your
organizations you don't have to justify
a pseudo account generic ID you don't
have to deal with 180 day expiration day
pad tokens you don't have any of that
that all goes away there's no secondary
you know Vault Storage for the primary
secret key for the SSH that goes with
the generic account so that you can just
change that when it finally expires so
you can force it or re reissue it and
then have you know the secret Keys
managed on on the generic the the level
of complexity or and God help you if you
feel like you have to have a GitHub
application ID with an installation
token just to do something that you
could have done with go mod vendor so so
by accepting the fact that you are
bringing in all of the source code
dependencies they're no longer external
dependencies because now they are
effective internal dependencies that
have been organized under the vendor
directory they are external dependencies
but they are explicitly managed external
depend dependencies that are present and
accountable under the vendor directory
and and I'm trying to be as clear as I
can about this but the takeaway of this
video is that go mod vendor bypasses any
problem you could ever have by having
your project depend on one or more
external private repos which GitHub
Enterprise cloud forces every single git
repo to
become and and I that is a problem
that's been presented by the by by Go's
assumption on public repos and if you
ask me I mean you know I've watched
other people who have said that they
didn't want any solution that couldn't
also be done by the user from the
command line go mod vendor is the
easiest of those Solutions if if your
primary Criterion if your primary
requirement for this solution is that it
should be usable by interactively by a
developer go mod vendor is the
definition of easy to Ed by a
developer so get over your version for
go mod vendor in my opinion and try it
out and see if it saves you a lot of
time if it helps you bypass all the
hassle by having you know private repo
dependencies and please please please
stop making monor repos that's a
horrible idea